RAMITH HETTIARACHCHI

SUMMARY

I'm interested in developing algorithms and fusing insights from machine learning (ML) to advance biology and healthcare, while striving for robustness and interpretability.

Research Interests : Computational Biology ML for Science Multi-modal Learning (Genomics+Imaging)

Research Directions: Combinatorial Optimization Uncertainty Quantification Graph Theory/Representation Learning

EDUCATION

University of Moratuwa

Sri Lanka

B.Sc. Eng(Hons.) Electronic & Telecommunication Engineering

Oct 2017 - June 2022

Dean's List: Semesters 1,2,3,4,6,7,8
 Thesis Title: "Hardware Accelerated Imaging Cytometry Modality Using Diffractive Deep Neural Networks"

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

JULY 2022 - Present | Post Baccalaureate Fellow, Division of Science, Harvard University

With the guidance of Dr. Sergey Ovchinnikov, my research focused on two projects related to Computational Biology: 1) A new method for phylogenetic tree search, 2) probing protein dynamics information using representations of the AlphaFold model and data from nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) experiments.

Furthermore, I developed quantization-aware training methods and robust optical neural networks with the guidance of Dr. Dushan Wadduwage.

neural networks with the guidance of Dr. Dushan Wadduwage

OCT 2020 - MAR 2021 | Research Intern at CSIRO Data61, Australia

Developed a robot capable of 3D reconstruction from Intel Realsense D435 camera data and performing dynamic obstacle avoidance using the D* lite algorithm.

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] A. Ahmad, R. Hettiarachchi*, A. Khezri*, B. S. Ahluwalia, D.N. Wadduwage, R. Ahmad, "Highly sensitive quantitative phase microscopy and deep learning complement whole genome sequencing for rapid detection of infection and antimicrobial resistance," *Frontiers in Microbiology (2023).* doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1154620

 → Antimicrobial Resistance Genomics and Imaging
- [2] H. Arguello, J. Bacca, H. Kariyawasam, E. Vargas, M. Marquez, <u>R. Hettiarachchi</u>, H. Garcia, K. Herath, U. Haputhanthri, B. S. Ahluwalia, P. So, D. N. Wadduwage, C. U. S. Edussooriya, "Deep Optical Coding Design in Computational Imaging". *IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, Jan 2023.* doi.org/10.1109/MSP.2022.3200173

 → Tutorial Paper

Conference/Workshop Publications

- [1] R. Hettiarachchi, Avi Swartz, S. Ovchinnikov, "Differentiable Search of Evolutionary Trees" → Accepted to International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2023 Workshops: "Sampling and Optimization in Discrete Space" (SODS) and "Differentiable Almost Everything" (DiffAE). doi.org/10.1101/2023.07.23.550206 → Evolutionary Biology Soft Combinatorial Optimization Graph Theory
- [2] R. Hettiarachchi, U. Haputhanthri, K. Herath, H. Kariyawasam, S. Munasinghe, K. Wickramasinghe, D. Samarasinghe, A. C. De Silva and C. U. S. Edussooriya, "A Novel Transfer Learning Based Approach for Screening Pre-existing Heart Diseases using Synchronized ECG Signals and Heart Sounds," *IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS)*, 2021, pp. 1-5, doi.org/10.1109/ISCAS51556.2021.9401093.
 - \hookrightarrow Transfer-learning ECG \leftrightarrow PCG CNN

INVITED TALKS

- [1] "Towards Realizable Optical Meta-surfaces through Physics-informed Quantization Aware Training", Northeast Symposium on Biomedical Optics Nov, 2022 MIT, Lansdowne St. [link]
- [2] "Towards Realizable D2NN Designs Through Quantization Aware Training", Nano-SymBioSys workshop at UiT, The Arctic University of Norway Sep, 2022 Tromsø, Norway. [link]

PATENT APPLICATIONS

[1] K. Herath*, U. Haputhanthri*, <u>R. Hettiarachchi</u>*, H. Kariyawasam*, A. Ahmad, B. S. Ahluwalia, C. U. S. Edussooriya and D. Wadduwage, "Provisional Application – Harvard Ref. No. HU 8932 - F&L Ref. 098930-0366 "Differentiable Microscopy Designs an All-Optical Quantitative Phase Microscope".

OTHER RESEARCH PROJECTS

Configuring an Intelligent Reflecting (IRS) Surface for Wireless Communications

Feb - June, 2021

Supervisor : Dr. Prathapasinghe Dharmawansa, University of Moratuwa.

 \blacktriangleright Developed an alternative optimization procedure based on a genetic algorithm and the adaptive moment estimation optimizer to find optimized IRS configurations in a 2^{4096} search space. It provided the best data rate and computational cost trade-off, and was the winning solution of the IEEE Signal Processing Cup 2021.

Genetic algorithm based optimization Mathematical Modeling

Realtime Sign Language Translation to Speech

Jul - Nov, 2019

Self supervised project.

▶ Developed a solution capable of mapping the EMG signals obtained by an arm to sign language gestures using an ML model. For high-performance inference, the DE-10 Nano field-programmable gate array is used. Project won the Iron Award at the APAC Finals of innovate FPGA, a global FPGA design contest organized by Intel.

Electromyography (EMG) Pattern Recognition

Honors, Awards, and Competitions

	2022
Scholar - 2022 Princeton Pathways to Graduate School program	
Winner - IEEE Signal Processing Cup, ICASSP - $Team T^3$	
1st in Sri Lanka, 48th in the World - IEEEXtreme 13.0 Competitive Programming - <i>Team Siraa</i> [link]	
Asia-Pacific - Iron Award - InnovateFPGA - Global FPGA Design Contest by Intel	
Mahapola Merit Scholarship - Awarded for students who excelled at the university entrance exam	
Sri Lankan Team Reserve - International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI)	

Volunteering / Leadership

Project Aya, Cohere For AI	Contributing to Sinhala Language Datasets	2023
IEEE SIGNAL PROCESSING SOCIETY, UOM.	Vice-Chairman, Chairman	2020 - 2022
ROTARACT CLUB OF UNIV. OF MORATUWA	Volunteer, Senior Director - IT	2019 - 2021
Sustainable Education Foundation	Assistant Program Manager - ScholarX	2020 - 2021
Socratic.org	Helping students with Chemistry & Math	2014 - 2016

PROGRAMMING PROFICIENCY

Languages: C/C++, Python, Scilab, MATLAB, Mathematica.

VISUALIZATION/TECHNICAL: Javascript, Processing, Git, LATEX.

LIBRARIES: JAX, OpenCV, PyTorch.

Relevant Coursework

SIGNAL PROCESSING: Genomic Signal Processing BM4321 (A+), Digital Signal Processing EN2570 (A),

Random Signals and Processes EN2040 (A), Signals and Systems EN1060 (A-)

MATHEMATICS: Calculus MA2023 (A+), Graph Theory MA2053 (A+), Linear Algebra MA2033 (A+)

COMPUTER VISION Fundamentals of Image Processing and Machine Vision EN2550 (A),

Machine Vision EN4553 (A+), Advances in Machine Vision EN4583 (A+)

References available upon request.

December, 2023